<sect2><title>&nbsp;</title><para>&nbsp;</para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Glibc installation</title>

<para>Glibc will check for the <filename>/etc/ld.so.conf</filename> file
and abort with an error if the file is missing, so we must create it:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>touch /etc/ld.so.conf</userinput></screen></para>

<para>The documentation that comes with Glibc recommends to build the package
not in the source directory but in a separate, dedicated directory:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>mkdir ../glibc-build &amp;&amp;
cd ../glibc-build</userinput></screen></para>

<para>Next, prepare Glibc to be compiled:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>CFLAGS="-O2 -pipe" \
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;../glibc-&glibc-version;/configure --prefix=/usr \
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;--disable-profile --enable-add-ons \
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;--libexecdir=/usr/bin \
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;--with-headers=/usr/include \
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;--mandir=/usr/share/man --infodir=/usr/share/info</userinput></screen></para>

<para>The meaning of the configure options are:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><userinput>--disable-profile</userinput>: This disables the
building of the libraries with profiling information. Omit this option if you
plan to do profiling.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><userinput>--enable-add-ons</userinput>: This enables any
add-ons that we installed with Glibc, in our case Linuxthreads.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para><userinput>--libexecdir=/usr/bin</userinput>: This will
cause the <filename>pt_chown</filename> program to be installed in the
<filename>/usr/bin</filename> directory.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>During this stage you will see the following warning:</para>

<blockquote><screen>configure: warning:
*** These auxiliary programs are missing or too old: msgfmt
*** some features will be disabled.
*** Check the INSTALL file for required versions.</screen></blockquote>

<para>The missing <filename>msgfmt</filename> program (from the Gettext
package, which we'll install later) won't cause any problems. The
<filename>msgfmt</filename> is used to generate the binary translation
files that can make your system talk in a different language. Because these
translation files have already been generated for you, there is no need for
<filename>msgfmt</filename>. You'd only need the program if you change the
translation source files (the <filename>*.po</filename> files in the
<filename class="directory">po</filename> subdirectory), which
would require you to regenerate the binary files.</para>

<para>Continue with compiling the package:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>make</userinput></screen></para>

<para>We'll continue with installing the package. The Linuxthreads man
pages are not going to be installed at this point because it requires a
working Perl installation. We'll install Perl later on in this chapter,
and the man pages will be installed when Glibc is installed for the second
time at the end of this chapter.</para>

<para><screen><userinput>make check</userinput></screen></para>

<para><screen><userinput>make install</userinput></screen></para>

<para>The locales (used by Glibc to make your Linux system talk in a different
language) weren't installed when you ran the previous command, so we have to
do that ourselves now:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>make localedata/install-locales</userinput></screen></para>

<para>An alternative to running the previous command is to install only those
locales which you need or want. This can be achieved using the localedef
command. Information on this can be found in the <filename>INSTALL</filename>
file in the <filename>glibc-&glibc-version;</filename> tree.</para>

<para>To finish off the installation we'll reload Bash so it will use the new
<filename>libnss_*</filename> files. This will also get rid of the
<emphasis>I have no name!</emphasis> message in the command prompt:</para>

<para><screen><userinput>exec /static/bin/bash --login</userinput></screen></para>

</sect2>

