<sect2>
<title>Other list modes</title>

<para>
The modes you can set yourself to require you to send an email to
<ulink url="mailto:listar@linuxfromscratch.org">
listar@linuxfromscratch.org</ulink>. The modes themselves are set by writing
the appropriate commands in the subject headers of the message.
</para>

<para>
As the name implies, the <emphasis>Set command</emphasis> tells you what
to write to set a mode. The <emphasis>Unset command</emphasis> tells
you what to write to unset a mode.
</para>

<para>
Replace listname in the example subject headers with the listname to which 
you want to apply the mode to. If you want to set more than one mode (to
the same list or multiple lists) with one email, you can do so by writing 
junk in the subject header like "hello" and then put the commands in the 
body of the message instead.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Digests</title>

<literallayout>
Set command: <emphasis>set listname digest</emphasis>
Unset command: <emphasis>unset listname digest</emphasis>
</literallayout>

<para>
All lists have the digest mode available and you can set yourself to
digest mode after you subscribe to a list. Being in digest mode will
cause you to stop receiving individual messages as they are posted to
the list and instead you will receive one email daily containing all
the messages posted to the list during that day.
</para>

<para>
There is a second digest mode called digest2. When you are set to this
mode you will receive the daily digests but you will also continue to
receive the individual messages to the lists as they are posted. To
set yourself to this mode write <emphasis>digest2</emphasis> instead of
<emphasis>digest</emphasis> in the subject header.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Vacation</title>

<literallayout>
Set command: <emphasis>set listname vacation</emphasis>
Unset command: <emphasis>unset listname vacation</emphasis>
</literallayout>

<para>
If you are going to be away for a while or wish to stop receiving
messages from the lists but you don't want to unsubscribe, you can set
yourself to vacation mode. This has the same effect as unsubscribing
yourself, but you don't have to go through the unsubscribe process and
then later through the subscribe process again.
</para>

</sect2>

