<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>
<sect1 id="pf-foreword">
<title>Foreword</title>
<?dbhtml filename="foreword.html"?>

<para>My adventures in Linux began six years ago when I downloaded and
installed my first distribution. After working with it for awhile, I
discovered issues I definitely would have liked to see improved upon.
For example, I didn't like the arrangement of the bootscripts or the way
programs were configured by default. I tried a number of alternate
distributions to address these issues, yet each had its pros and cons.
Finally, I realized that if I wanted full satisfaction from my Linux
system, I would have to build my own from scratch.</para>

<para>What does this mean? I resolved not to use pre-compiled packages
of any kind, nor CD-ROMs or boot disks that would install basic
utilities. I would use my current Linux system to develop my own
customized system. This <quote>perfect</quote> Linux system would then
have the strengths of various systems without their associated
weaknesses. In the beginning, the idea was rather daunting, but I
remained committed to the idea that a system could be built that would
conform to my needs and desires rather than to a standard that just
did not fit what I was looking for.</para>

<para>After sorting through issues such as circular dependencies and
compile-time errors, I created a custom-built Linux system that was
fully operational and suitable to individual needs. This process also
allowed me to create compact and streamlined Linux systems which are
faster and take up less space than traditional operating systems. I
called this system a Linux From Scratch system, or an LFS system for
short.</para>

<para>As I shared my goals and experiences with other members of the
Linux community, it became apparent that there was sustained interest
in the ideas set forth in my Linux adventures. Such custom-built LFS
systems not only to meet user specifications and requirements, but
also serve as an ideal learning opportunity for programmers and system
administrators to enhance their Linux skills. Out of this broadened
interest, the Linux From Scratch Project was born.</para>

<para>This <emphasis>Linux From Scratch</emphasis> book provides
readers with the background and instruction to design and build custom
Linux systems. This book highlights the Linux from Scratch project and
the benefits of using this system. Users can dictate all aspects of
their system, including directory layout, script setup, and security.
The resulting system will be compiled straight from the source code,
and the user will be able to specify where, why, and how programs are
installed. This book allows readers to fully customize Linux systems
to their own needs and allows users more control over their
system.</para>

<para>I hope you will have a great time working on your own LFS
system, and enjoy the numerous benefits of having a system that is
truly <emphasis>your own</emphasis>.</para>

<para></para>

<literallayout>--
Gerard Beekmans
gerard@linuxfromscratch.org</literallayout>

</sect1>

