<sect1 id="ch10-theend">
<title>The End</title>

<para>
Well done! You have finished installing your LFS system. It may have
been a long process but it was well worth it. We wish you a lot of fun
with your new shiny custom built Linux system.
</para>

<para>
Now would be a good time to strip all debug and compiler symbols from 
the binaries on your LFS system. If you are not a programmer and don't plan 
on debugging your software, then you will be happy to know that you can 
reclaim a few tens of megs by removing debug symbols. This process causes 
no inconvenience other than not being able to debug the software fully 
anymore, which is not an issue if you don't know how to debug. You can 
remove the symbols by executing the following command:
</para>

<blockquote><literallayout>
	<userinput>find / -type f -exec strip --strip-unneeded '{}' ';'
	</userinput>
</literallayout></blockquote>

<para>
If you plan to ever upgrade to a newer LFS version in the future it
will be a good idea to create the /etc/lfs-&version; file. By having
this file it is very easy for you (and for us if you are going to ask
for help with something at some point) to find out which LFS version
you have installed on your system. This can just be a null-byte file by
running:
</para>

<blockquote><literallayout>
	<userinput>touch /etc/lfs-&version;</userinput>
</literallayout></blockquote>

<para>
If you are wondering: "Well, where to go now?" you'll be glad to hear that
someone has written an <ulink
url="http://archive.linuxfromscratch.org/lfs-hints/Afterlfs.txt">LFS-Hint</ulink>
on that subject. On a same note, if you are not only newbie to LFS, but also
newbie to Linux in general, you may find the <ulink
url="http://archive.linuxfromscratch.org/lfs-hints/newbie.txt">newbie
hint</ulink> very interesting.
</para>

<para>
Don't forget there are several LFS mailinglists you can subscribe to if
you are in need of help, advice, etc. See 
<ulink url="ch01-maillists.html">Chapter 1 - Mailinglists</ulink> for
more information.
</para>

<para>
Again, we thank you for using the LFS Book and hope you found this book
useful and worth your time.
</para>

</sect1>

