<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>
<sect1 id="ch-tools-glibc" role="wrap">
<title>Glibc-&glibc-version;</title>
<?dbhtml filename="glibc.html"?>

<indexterm zone="ch-tools-glibc">
<primary sortas="a-Glibc">Glibc</primary>
<secondary>tools</secondary></indexterm>

<sect2 role="package"><title/>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../chapter06/glibc.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/sect1/sect2[1]/para[1])"/>

<segmentedlist>
<segtitle>&buildtime;</segtitle>
<segtitle>&diskspace;</segtitle>
<seglistitem><seg>11.8 SBU</seg><seg>800 MB</seg></seglistitem>
</segmentedlist>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../chapter06/glibc.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/sect1/sect2[1]/segmentedlist[2])"/>

</sect2>

<sect2 role="installation">
<title>Installation of Glibc</title>

<para>This package is known to have issues when its default
optimization flags (including the <parameter>-march</parameter> and
<parameter>-mcpu</parameter> options) are changed. If any environment
variables that override default optimizations have been defined, such
as <envar>CFLAGS</envar> and <envar>CXXFLAGS</envar>,
unset them when building Glibc.</para>

<para>It should be noted that compiling Glibc in any way other than
the method suggested in this book puts the stability of the system at
risk.</para>

<para>The Glibc documentation recommends building Glibc outside of the source
directory in a dedicated build directory:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir ../glibc-build
cd ../glibc-build</userinput></screen>

<para>Next, prepare Glibc for compilation:</para>

<screen><userinput>../glibc-&glibc-version;/configure --prefix=/tools \
    --disable-profile --enable-add-ons \
    --enable-kernel=2.6.0 --with-binutils=/tools/bin \
    --without-gd --without-cvs --with-headers=/tools/include \
    --without-selinux</userinput></screen>

<para>The meaning of the configure options:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--disable-profile</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This builds the libraries without profiling
information. Omit this option if profiling on the temporary tools is
necessary.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--enable-add-ons</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This tells Glibc to use the NPTL add-on as its threading 
library.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--enable-kernel=2.6.0</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This tells Glibc to compile the library with support
for 2.6.x Linux kernels.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--with-binutils=/tools/bin</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>While not required, this switch ensures that there are
no errors pertaining to which Binutils programs get used during the
Glibc build.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--without-gd</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This prevents the build of the
<command>memusagestat</command> program, which insists on linking
against the host's libraries (libgd, libpng, libz,
etc.).</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--without-cvs</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This prevents the Makefile files from
attempting automatic CVS checkouts when using a CVS snapshot. While
this command is not required, it is recommended because it suppresses
an annoying, but harmless, warning about a missing autoconf
program.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--with-headers=/tools/include</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This tells Glibc to compile itself against the headers recently
installed to the tools directory, so that it knows exactly what features the
kernel has and can optimize itself accordingly.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<!-- Edit Me -->
<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--without-selinux</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>When building from hosts using SELinux functionality
(i.e. Fedora Core 3), glibc will try to integrate this functionality into
itself, but will fail, because we do not have this functionality in the LFS
tools environment.  This option will disable this, allowing glibc to build
correctly, but will not otherwise affect the build.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<!-- -->
</variablelist>

<para>During this stage the following warning might appear:</para>

<blockquote><screen><computeroutput>configure: WARNING:
*** These auxiliary programs are missing or 
*** incompatible versions: msgfmt
*** some features will be disabled.
*** Check the INSTALL file for required versions.</computeroutput></screen></blockquote>

<para>The missing or incompatible <command>msgfmt</command> program is
generally harmless, but it can sometimes cause issues when running the
test suite. This <command>msgfmt</command> program is part of the
Gettext package which the host distribution should provide. If
<command>msgfmt</command> is present but deemed incompatible, upgrade
the host system's Gettext package or continue without it and see if
the test suite runs without problems regardless.</para>

<para>Compile the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make</userinput></screen>

<para>Compilation is now complete. As mentioned earlier, running the
test suites for the temporary tools installed in this chapter is not
mandatory. To run the Glibc test suite (if desired), the following
command will do so:</para>

<screen><userinput>make check</userinput></screen>

<para>For a discussion of test failures that are of particular
importance, please see <xref linkend="ch-system-glibc" role="."/></para>

<para>In this chapter, some tests can be adversely effected by
existing tools or environmental issues on the host system. Glibc test
suite failures in this chapter are typically not worrisome. The Glibc
installed in <xref linkend="chapter-building-system"/> is the one that
will ultimately end up being used, so that is the one that needs to pass
most tests (even in <xref linkend="chapter-building-system"/>, some
failures could still occur, for example, with the math tests).</para>

<para>When experiencing a failure, make a note of it, then continue by
reissuing the <command>make check</command> command. The test suite should pick up where it left
off and continue. This stop-start sequence can be circumvented by
issuing a <command>make -k check</command> command. If using this option, be sure to log the
output so that the log file can be examined for failures later.</para>

<para>The install stage of Glibc will issue a harmless warning at the
end about the absence of <filename>/tools/etc/ld.so.conf</filename>. 
Prevent this warning with:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir /tools/etc
touch /tools/etc/ld.so.conf</userinput></screen>

<para>Install the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make install</userinput></screen>

<para>Different countries and cultures have varying conventions for
how to communicate. These conventions range from the format for
representing dates and times to more complex issues, such as the
language spoken. The <quote>internationalization</quote> of GNU
programs works by locale.</para>

<note><para>If the test suites are not being run in this chapter (as
per the recommendation), there is no need to install the locales now.
The appropriate locales will be installed in the next
chapter.</para></note>

<para>To install the Glibc locales anyway, use the following
command:</para>

<screen><userinput>make localedata/install-locales</userinput></screen>

<para>To save time, an alternative to running the
previous command (which generates and installs every locale Glibc is
aware of) is to install only those locales that are wanted and needed.
This can be achieved by using the <command>localedef</command>
command. Information on this command is located in the
<filename>INSTALL</filename> file in the Glibc source.  However, there
are a number of locales that are essential in order for the tests of
future packages to pass, in particular, the
<emphasis>libstdc++</emphasis> tests from GCC. The following
instructions, instead of the <parameter>install-locales</parameter>
target used above, will install the minimum set of locales necessary
for the tests to run successfully:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -p /tools/lib/locale
localedef -i de_DE -f ISO-8859-1 de_DE
localedef -i de_DE@euro -f ISO-8859-15 de_DE@euro
localedef -i en_HK -f ISO-8859-1 en_HK
localedef -i en_PH -f ISO-8859-1 en_PH
localedef -i en_US -f ISO-8859-1 en_US
localedef -i es_MX -f ISO-8859-1 es_MX
localedef -i fa_IR -f UTF-8 fa_IR
localedef -i fr_FR -f ISO-8859-1 fr_FR
localedef -i fr_FR@euro -f ISO-8859-15 fr_FR@euro
localedef -i it_IT -f ISO-8859-1 it_IT
localedef -i ja_JP -f EUC-JP ja_JP</userinput></screen>

</sect2>

<sect2 role="content"><title/>
<para>Details on this package are located in <xref
linkend="contents-glibc" role="."/></para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

