<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>
<sect1 id="ch-tools-glibc" role="wrap">
<title>Glibc-&glibc-version;</title>
<?dbhtml filename="glibc.html"?>

<indexterm zone="ch-tools-glibc">
<primary sortas="a-Glibc">Glibc</primary>
<secondary>tools</secondary></indexterm>

<sect2 role="package"><title/>
<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../chapter06/glibc.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/sect1/sect2[1]/para[1])"/>

<segmentedlist>
<segtitle>&buildtime;</segtitle>
<segtitle>&diskspace;</segtitle>
<seglistitem><seg>11.8 SBU</seg><seg>800 MB</seg></seglistitem>
</segmentedlist>

<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../chapter06/glibc.xml" xpointer="xpointer(/sect1/sect2[1]/segmentedlist[2])"/>

</sect2>

<sect2 role="installation">
<title>Installation of Glibc</title>

<para>This package is known to behave badly when you change its default
optimization flags (including the <parameter>-march</parameter> and
<parameter>-mcpu</parameter> options). Therefore, if you have defined any
environment variables that override default optimizations, such as CFLAGS and
CXXFLAGS, we recommend un-setting them when building Glibc.</para>

<para>Basically, compiling Glibc in any other way than the book suggests
is putting the stability of your system at risk.</para>

<para>The Glibc documentation recommends building Glibc outside of the source
directory in a dedicated build directory:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir ../glibc-build
cd ../glibc-build</userinput></screen>

<para>Next, prepare Glibc for compilation:</para>

<screen><userinput>../glibc-&glibc-version;/configure --prefix=/tools \
    --disable-profile --enable-add-ons=nptl --with-tls \
    --with-__thread --enable-kernel=2.6.0 --with-binutils=/tools/bin \
    --without-gd --without-cvs</userinput></screen>

<para>The meaning of the configure options:</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--disable-profile</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This builds the
libraries without profiling information. Omit this option if you plan to do
profiling on the temporary tools.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--enable-add-ons=nptl</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This tells Glibc to use the NPTL add-on as its threading 
library.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--with-tls</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This tells Glibc to include support for TLS (thread-local storage).
This is required for NPTL to work. </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--with-__thread</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This tells Glibc to include thread support, this is for proper
compiling of the thread-local storage.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--enable-kernel=2.6.0</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This tells Glibc to compile the library for support of
linux 2.6.x kernels.
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--with-binutils=/tools/bin</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>Strictly speaking this switch is not required. But it does ensure 
nothing can go wrong with regard to what Binutils programs get used during the 
Glibc build.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--without-gd</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This prevents the build of the <command>memusagestat</command>
program, which strangely enough insists on linking against the host's libraries 
(libgd, libpng, libz, and so forth). </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><parameter>--without-cvs</parameter></term>
<listitem><para>This is meant to prevent
the Makefiles from attempting automatic CVS checkouts when using a CVS
snapshot. But it's not actually needed these days. We use it because it
suppresses an annoying but harmless warning about a missing
<command>autoconf</command> program.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>During this stage you might see the following warning:</para>

<blockquote><screen><computeroutput>configure: WARNING:
*** These auxiliary programs are missing or incompatible versions: msgfmt
*** some features will be disabled.
*** Check the INSTALL file for required versions.</computeroutput></screen></blockquote>

<para>The missing or incompatible <command>msgfmt</command> program is
generally harmless, but it's believed it can sometimes cause problems when
running the test suite.</para>

<para>Compile the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make</userinput></screen>

<para>Compilation is now complete. As mentioned earlier, running the test suites
for the temporary tools installed in this chapter is not mandatory. If you want
to run the Glibc test suite though, the following command will do so:</para>

<screen><userinput>make check</userinput></screen>

<para>For a discussion of test failures that are of particular
importance, please see <xref linkend="ch-system-glibc"/>.</para>

<para>In this chapter, some tests can be adversely affected by existing tools or
environmental issues on the host system.  In short, don't worry too much if you
see Glibc test suite failures in this chapter. The Glibc in
<xref linkend="chapter-building-system"/> is the one we'll ultimately end up
using, so that is the one we would really like to see pass the tests (but even
there some failures could still occur -- the <emphasis>math</emphasis> tests,
for example).</para>

<para>When experiencing a failure, make a note of it, then continue by reissuing
the <command>make check</command>. The test suite should pick up where it left
off and continue. You can circumvent this stop-start sequence by issuing a
<command>make -k check</command>. If you do that though, be sure to log the
output so that you can later peruse the log file and examine the total number of
failures.</para>

<para>Though it is a harmless message, the install stage of Glibc will at the
end complain about the absence of <filename>/tools/etc/ld.so.conf</filename>.
Prevent this confusing little warning with:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir /tools/etc
touch /tools/etc/ld.so.conf</userinput></screen>

<para>Now install the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make install</userinput></screen>

<para>Different countries and cultures have varying conventions for how to
communicate. These conventions range from very simple ones, such as the format
for representing dates and times, to very complex ones, such as the language
spoken. The <quote>internationalization</quote> of GNU programs works by means
of <emphasis>locales</emphasis>.</para>

<note><para>If you are not running the test suites here in this chapter as per
our recommendation, there is little point in installing the locales now. We'll
be installing the locales in the next chapter.</para></note>

<para>If you still want to install the Glibc locales anyway, the following
command will do so:</para>

<screen><userinput>make localedata/install-locales</userinput></screen>

<para>An alternative to running the previous command is to install only those
locales which you need or want. This can be achieved by using the
<command>localedef</command> command. Information on this can be found in
the <filename>INSTALL</filename> file in the Glibc source. However, there are
a number of locales that are essential for the tests of future packages to
pass, in particular, the <emphasis>libstdc++</emphasis> tests from GCC. The
following instructions, instead of the install-locales target above, will
install the minimum set of locales necessary for the tests to run
successfully:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -p /tools/lib/locale
localedef -i de_DE -f ISO-8859-1 de_DE
localedef -i de_DE@euro -f ISO-8859-15 de_DE@euro
localedef -i en_HK -f ISO-8859-1 en_HK
localedef -i en_PH -f ISO-8859-1 en_PH
localedef -i en_US -f ISO-8859-1 en_US
localedef -i es_MX -f ISO-8859-1 es_MX
localedef -i fa_IR -f UTF-8 fa_IR
localedef -i fr_FR -f ISO-8859-1 fr_FR
localedef -i fr_FR@euro -f ISO-8859-15 fr_FR@euro
localedef -i it_IT -f ISO-8859-1 it_IT
localedef -i ja_JP -f EUC-JP ja_JP</userinput></screen>

</sect2>

<sect2 role="content"><title/>
<para>The details on this package are found in <xref linkend="contents-glibc"/>.</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>
