<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>

<sect1 id="ch-tools-glibc" role="wrap">
  <?dbhtml filename="glibc.html"?>

  <title>Glibc-&glibc-version;</title>

  <indexterm zone="ch-tools-glibc">
    <primary sortas="a-Glibc">Glibc</primary>
    <secondary>tools</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <sect2 role="package">
    <title/>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
    href="../chapter06/glibc.xml"
    xpointer="xpointer(/sect1/sect2[1]/para[1])"/>

    <segmentedlist>
      <segtitle>&buildtime;</segtitle>
      <segtitle>&diskspace;</segtitle>

      <seglistitem>
        <seg>&glibc-ch5-sbu;</seg>
        <seg>&glibc-ch5-du;</seg>
      </seglistitem>
    </segmentedlist>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 role="installation">
    <title>Installation of Glibc</title>

    <para>Apply a patch to obtain various fixes that the upstream maintainers
    have provided:</para>

<screen><userinput>patch -Np1 -i ../&glibc-branch_update-patch;</userinput></screen>

    <para>The Glibc documentation recommends building Glibc outside of the source
    directory in a dedicated build directory:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -v ../glibc-build
cd ../glibc-build</userinput></screen>

    <para>Next, prepare Glibc for compilation:</para>

<screen><userinput>../glibc-&glibc-version;/configure --prefix=/tools \
    --disable-profile --enable-add-ons \
    --enable-kernel=2.6.0 --with-binutils=/tools/bin \
    --without-gd --with-headers=/tools/include \
    --without-selinux</userinput></screen>

    <variablelist>
      <title>The meaning of the configure options:</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><parameter>--disable-profile</parameter></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This builds the libraries without profiling information. Omit
          this option if profiling on the temporary tools is necessary.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><parameter>--enable-add-ons</parameter></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This tells Glibc to use the NPTL add-on as its threading
          library.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><parameter>--enable-kernel=2.6.0</parameter></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This tells Glibc to compile the library with support
          for 2.6.x Linux kernels.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><parameter>--with-binutils=/tools/bin</parameter></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>While not required, this switch ensures that there are
          no errors pertaining to which Binutils programs get used during the
          Glibc build.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><parameter>--without-gd</parameter></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This prevents the build of the <command>memusagestat</command>
          program, which insists on linking against the host's libraries
          (libgd, libpng, libz, etc.).</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><parameter>--with-headers=/tools/include</parameter></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This tells Glibc to compile itself against the headers recently
          installed to the tools directory, so that it knows exactly what
          features the kernel has and can optimize itself accordingly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><parameter>--without-selinux</parameter></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>When building from hosts that include SELinux functionality
          (e.g., Fedora Core 3), Glibc will build with support for SELinux.
          As the LFS tools environment does not contain support for SELinux, a
          Glibc compiled with such support will fail to operate correctly.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <para>During this stage the following warning might appear:</para>

    <blockquote>
<screen><computeroutput>configure: WARNING:
*** These auxiliary programs are missing or
*** incompatible versions: msgfmt
*** some features will be disabled.
*** Check the INSTALL file for required versions.</computeroutput></screen>
    </blockquote>

    <para>The missing or incompatible <command>msgfmt</command> program is
    generally harmless, but it can sometimes cause issues when running the
    test suite. This <command>msgfmt</command> program is part of the
    Gettext package which the host distribution should provide. If
    <command>msgfmt</command> is present but deemed incompatible, upgrade
    the host system's Gettext package or continue without it and see if
    the test suite runs without problems regardless.</para>

    <para>Compile the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make</userinput></screen>

    <para>Compilation is now complete. As mentioned earlier, running the
    test suites for the temporary tools installed in this chapter is not
    mandatory. To run the Glibc test suite (if desired), the following
    command will do so:</para>

<screen><userinput>make check</userinput></screen>

    <para>For a discussion of test failures that are of particular
    importance, please see <xref linkend="ch-system-glibc" role="."/></para>

    <para>In this chapter, some tests can be adversely affected by
    existing tools or environmental issues on the host system. Glibc test
    suite failures in this chapter are typically not worrisome. The Glibc
    installed in <xref linkend="chapter-building-system"/> is the one that
    will ultimately end up being used, so that is the one that needs to pass
    most tests (even in <xref linkend="chapter-building-system"/>, some
    failures could still occur, for example, with the math tests).</para>

    <para>When experiencing a failure, make a note of it, then continue by
    reissuing the <command>make check</command> command. The test suite
    should pick up where it left off and continue. This stop-start sequence
    can be circumvented by issuing a <command>make -k check</command> command.
    If using this option, be sure to log the output so that the log file can
    be examined for failures later.</para>

    <para>The install stage of Glibc will issue a harmless warning at the
    end about the absence of <filename>/tools/etc/ld.so.conf</filename>.
    Prevent this warning with:</para>

<screen><userinput>mkdir -v /tools/etc
touch /tools/etc/ld.so.conf</userinput></screen>

    <para>Install the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make install</userinput></screen>

    <para>Different countries and cultures have varying conventions for
    how to communicate. These conventions range from the format for
    representing dates and times to more complex issues, such as the
    language spoken. The <quote>internationalization</quote> of GNU
    programs works by locale.</para>

    <note>
      <para>If the test suites are not being run in this chapter (as per
      the recommendation), there is no need to install the locales now.
      The appropriate locales will be installed in the next chapter.
      To install the Glibc locales anyway, use instructions from
      <xref linkend="ch-system-glibc" role="."/></para>
    </note>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 role="content">
    <title/>

    <para>Details on this package are located in
    <xref linkend="contents-glibc" role="."/></para>

  </sect2>

</sect1>
