<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY % general-entities SYSTEM "../general.ent">
  %general-entities;
]>
<sect1 id="ch-tools-introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

<para>In this chapter we will compile and install a minimal
Linux system. This system will contain just enough tools to be able
to start constructing the final LFS system in the next chapter and allow
a working environment with a little more user convenience than a minimum
environment.</para>

<para>The building of this minimal system is done in two steps: first we
build a brand-new and host-independent toolchain (compiler, assembler,
linker, libraries, and a few useful utilities), and then use this to build all the other essential
tools.</para>

<para>The files compiled in this chapter will be installed under the
<filename class="directory">$LFS/tools</filename> directory
to keep them separate from the files installed in the next chapter and your host's production directories.
Since the packages compiled here are merely temporary, we don't want
them to pollute the soon-to-be LFS system.</para>

<para>Before issuing the build instructions for a package, you are expected to
have already unpacked it (explained shortly) as user <emphasis>lfs</emphasis>,
and to have performed a <userinput>cd</userinput> into the created directory.
The build instructions assume that you are using the <command>bash</command>
shell.</para>

<para>Several of the packages are patched before compilation, but only when
the patch is needed to circumvent a problem. Often the patch is needed in
both this and the next chapter, but sometimes in only one of them. Therefore,
don't worry when instructions for a downloaded patch seem to be missing. Also,
when applying a patch, you'll occasionally see warning messages about
<emphasis>offset</emphasis> or <emphasis>fuzz</emphasis>. These warnings are
nothing to worry about, as the patch was still successfully applied.</para>

<para>During the compilation of most packages you will see many warnings
scroll by on your screen. These are normal and can safely be ignored. They are
just what they say they are: warnings -- mostly about deprecated, but not
invalid, use of the C or C++ syntax. It's just that C standards have changed
rather often and some packages still use the older standard, which is not
really a problem.</para>

<para>After installing each package you should delete its source and build
directories, <emphasis>unless</emphasis> told otherwise. Deleting the sources
saves space, but also prevents mis-configuration when the same package is
reinstalled further on. Only for three packages you will need to keep the
source and build directories around for a while, so their contents can be used
by later commands. Do not miss the reminders.</para>

<para>Now first check that your LFS environment variable is set up
properly:</para>

<screen><userinput>echo $LFS</userinput></screen>

<para>Make sure the output shows the path to your LFS partition's mount
point, which is <filename class="directory">/mnt/lfs</filename> if you
followed our example.</para>

</sect1>
