<sect1 id="ch-tools-tcl" xreflabel="Tcl">
<title>Installing Tcl-&tcl-version;</title>
<?dbhtml filename="tcl.html" dir="chapter05"?>

<para>The Tcl package contains the Tool Command Language.</para>

<screen>&buildtime; &tcl-time-tools; 
&diskspace; &tcl-compsize-tools;</screen>

&aa-tcl-down;
&aa-tcl-dep;

<sect2><title>&nbsp;</title><para>&nbsp;</para></sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Installation of Tcl</title>

<para>This package and the next two are only installed to be able to run the 
test suites for GCC and Binutils. Installing three packages just for testing 
purposes may seem like overkill, but it is very reassuring, if not essential, 
to know that our most important tools are working properly. Even if you are
not running the test suites here in this chapter as per our recommendation,
these packages are still required for the test suites in the next
chapter.</para>

<para>Prepare Tcl for compilation:</para>

<screen><userinput>cd unix
./configure --prefix=/tools</userinput></screen>

<para>Build the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make</userinput></screen>

<para>(If you insist on testing the results, then issue:
<userinput>TZ=UTC make test</userinput>. However, the Tcl test suite is known
to experience failures under certain host conditions that are not fully
understood. Therefore, test suite failures here are not surprising, and are not
considered critical. The <emphasis>TZ=UTC</emphasis> parameter sets the time
zone to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) also known as Greenwich Mean Time
(GMT), but only for the duration of the test suite run. This ensures the clock
tests are exercised correctly. More information on the TZ environment variable
will be given later on in <xref linkend="chapter-bootscripts"/>.)</para>

<para>Install the package:</para>

<screen><userinput>make install</userinput></screen>

<!-- HACK - Force some whitespace to appease tidy -->
<literallayout></literallayout>

<warning><para><emphasis>Do not remove</emphasis> the
<filename>tcl&tcl-version;</filename> source directory yet, as the next package
will need its internal headers.</para></warning>

<!-- HACK - Force some whitespace to appease tidy -->
<literallayout></literallayout>

<para>And make a necessary symbolic link:</para>

<screen><userinput>ln -s tclsh8.4 /tools/bin/tclsh</userinput></screen>

</sect2>

&aa-tcl-shortdesc;
&aa-tcl-desc;

</sect1>

